<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Popish mercy and justice being an account, not of those (more than an hundred thousand) massacred in France by the papists, formerly, but of some later persecutions of the French Protestants : set forth in their petition to the French king / translated for the information of English Protestants, by Ezreel Tonge ...</title>
            <author>Tonge, Ezerel, 1621-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19498960</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19498960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108872</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55460)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1676:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Popish mercy and justice being an account, not of those (more than an hundred thousand) massacred in France by the papists, formerly, but of some later persecutions of the French Protestants : set forth in their petition to the French king / translated for the information of English Protestants, by Ezreel Tonge ...</title>
                  <author>Tonge, Ezerel, 1621-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Th. Dawks ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: pages [2] and 18.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  France.</term>
               <term>France --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108872:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Popiſh Mercy AND JUSTICE.</p>
            <p>Being An Account, not of thoſe (more than an hundred Thouſand) maſſacred in <hi>France</hi> by the Papiſts, formerly, but of ſome later Perſecutions of the <hi>French Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth in their PETITION to the FRENCH KING.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated for the Information of Engliſh Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ezreel Tonge,</hi> the firſt Diſcoverer of this moſt horrid Plot to His Majeſty.</p>
            <q>Crimine ab uno diſce omnes.</q>
            <q>
               <p>The tender mercies of the wicked are cruelties.</p>
               <p>—Behold the tears of ſuch as were oppreſſed, and they had no comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and on the ſide of their oppreſſors there was power.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>If thou ſeeſt the oppreſſion of the poor, and violent perverting of Judgement and Juſtice in a Province, marvel not at the matter: for he that is higher then the higheſt regardeth, and there are higher than they,</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 5.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Th. Dawks,</hi> and are to be ſold at the white Swan by Apothecarys hall in Black fryers. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:108872:2"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 10. 1678.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>There is preparing for the Preſs <hi>A Brief History of</hi> PRINTING; Dedicated to the Kings Majeſty, and both Houſes of Parliament: Very uſeful for all in Authority, and for Scholars. Written, for the good of Poſterity, by <hi>Thomas Dawks</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty in the Britiſh Language.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Hilary Term will be publiſht</hi> Horae Mathematicae <hi>ſeu</hi> URANIA; <hi>The Soul of Aſtrology:</hi> containing that Art in all its parts; wherein more eſpecially you will find 1. A <hi>New</hi> Diſcourſe on the 12 ſigns. 2. A refutation of the Planetary hour, Terms of the Planets, deep, pitted &amp; azimene degrees. 3. A <hi>new</hi> Method of managing Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties without trouble of Calculation, by Inſpection only. 4. A new Method of judging Directions. 5. A Compendium of <hi>Argol</hi>'s way. 6. A <hi>New</hi> Method of judging Horary Queſtions: 7. Judgment of Annual Revolutions of the World. 8. Of Monthly Obſervations, &amp; Meteorological Predictions. 9. Judgment of Eclipſes, Aſpects of the Planets &amp; Comets. 10. How to find the Planets and ſtars riſing, ſouthing and ſetting by <hi>new</hi> Tables never before publiſht. 11. The Reaſon and Demonſtration of the Aſpects of the Planets. 12. The various uſes of the Sexaginary Table: with many other things of excellent uſe, too tedious here to be related. And followed with</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Synopſis Medicinae,</hi> (ſo often mention'd in the <hi>New London Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſatory</hi>) Or, A Compendium of Phyſick, Chyrurgery and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimy; inlarged through all its Parts (aſtrologically propoſed, and chymically applyed:) among which you will find, 1. The Anatomy of the Body of Man. 2. The Order and Method of the Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Cheſt. 3. The Art of Embalming both after the Aegyptian and European wayes. 4. The 112 Arcanums of <hi>Joh. Pet. Faber.</hi> 5. The Proceſs of the Univerſal Medicine of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> as 'twas taken out of the Original Manuſcript. Both which are written by <hi>W. Salmon,</hi> Profeſſor of Phyſick, living at the red Balls in Salisbury Court, Fleetſtreet: and Printed by <hi>Th. Dawks,</hi> in Black-fryers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108872:2"/>
            <head>To the KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LEWIS de Liſle Eſquier, Lord of Ollon, Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick de Vins <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Lord of Barveil, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, Henry and Iſaac de Bloſſet Eſquiers; Claudius de Maumirey, and James le Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erre do moſt humbly remonſtrate to your Majeſty, That amongſt the Places of the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the Province of Burgundy, that of Vaujau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court near to Avalon, hath been well eſtabliſhed, and was confirmed by the Lord Bouchu Intendant of that Province; which the Rector of that Pariſh could not endure, nor the Gray Fryars of Vezelay, whoſe Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, named du Han, did not only bring the Proceſs againſt it to cauſe it to be forbidden and ſuppreſt, but did by Libels printed and publiſhed, and by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons endeavored to perſuade the People of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, That your Majeſty was reſolved to cauſe all the places of that Religion in that Province to be pulled down, and ſo likewiſe throughout all France, and not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108872:3"/> to tolerate the ſaid Reformed Religion therein any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. They conſpired to raiſe a ſeditious Tumult of the Catholick Communalty, as well of that place as of the Neighborhood againſt them of the ſaid Proteſtant Religion, and to take occaſion by a Synod, which was to be held at the ſaid Vaujaucourt, on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of June 1667. and the following dayes, that thereby they might at once drive away and deſtroy all the Miniſters in Burgundy: and to draw a Confluence of People to that Place, he cauſed publick Notice to be given all about every where of the Meeting of that Synod, and that his Deſign was to be there, and to diſpute againſt all the Miniſters, and to refute what they preached in their Sermons. And he did indeed appear there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, followed by multitudes of People: And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, upon his Arrival, he ſet up his Preaching Pulpit directly before the door of the Inn where all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Miniſters lodg'd, deſigning, that when they came either in or out, they might be expos'd to the mutinous people. And having ſpent the four firſt daies in Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſeditiouſly againſt the Doctrine of the Proteſtant Miniſters, and purſuing them with Challenges unto the Place of their Exerciſe, where he was attended by three or four thouſand Perſons, and continually affronting and inſulting over them, becauſe they would not Diſpute with them, on the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the ſaid June, he executed his miſchievous Deſign by ringing the Allarm-Bell, and by crying HARLAU, HARLAU, which is the Word there uſed to raiſe a Tumult, and which he gave the Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers himſelf: All whoſe Fury fell upon your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who (whilſt the Women, Children and feeble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſaved themſelves in ſeveral places) preſented themſelves to this inraged Multitude, endeavored to appeaſe them by ſweet paſſionate Intreaties: and the ſaid Lord Ollon principally, who being the Lord of that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108872:3"/> Place, believed that his Vaſſals would have had ſome Reſpect for him, and have aſſiſted him in putting a ſtop to that Diſorder; but he, as well as the reſt, was firſt outragiouſly abus'd in words, and then aſſaulted with Stones, Cudgels, Swords, Halberts, and Spits, knock'd down, wounded, and grievouſly bruiſed in all parts of their Bodyes, dragg'd by their hair to be caſt into the River; nor had the Murderers here deſiſted, but that 'twas thought they had been dead: One of them deſigning to diſpatch the Lord of Ollon, took up the heavieſt ſtone he could find, and threw it at his head with all his force: After they had done this, theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious people went and broke open the doors of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Houſes, and amongſt others, the houſe of Zachary and James Courcelles, in which the ſaid Miniſters and and others were lodged, which houſes they plundred: Now alſo ſome Women and other Catholicks improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their time, took up your Petitioners and carried them into the Caſtle of that place, where they lay a great while before they gave any ſign of life, having loſt, in a manner, all their Blood by the many wounds that were given them.</p>
            <p>As Violences that were ſo notorious could not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, your Petitioners ſent the 21 of the ſaid June, to preſent their Complaint to the ſaid Lord Bouchu, who gave Commiſſion to the Lord Guijon, Lieutenant Criminal of Avalon, to take Information thereof, and to take for his Aſſiſtant, of the pretended Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Lord Rey de Morand, a Councellor at Law, which was done the next day, and ſixty Witneſſes exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, as well of the one as of the other Religion, which related all the Circumſtances of the Sedition of which the ſaid Gray-fryer du Han having had Advice, and not doubting that he was charged as the principal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all that hapned, he went and inticed the Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108872:4"/> General of the Parliament of Dijon; who, upon his ſute, deputed the Lord Chaumelis, a Senator of the ſaid Parliament, to take Information of the ſame Fact; pretending againſt all appearance of Reaſon, That they of the Proteſtant Religion, who were not above 70 or or 80 perſons (compriſing in that number the Miniſters, Elders, Oldmen, Women and Children) had intended to abuſe them of the Catholick Religion, who were in number 6000 and more: and the ſame du Han, having cauſed himſelf to be examined, produced for witneſſes thoſe who were the moſt violent in the Aſſault and Plunder: Your Petitioners, being adviſed thereof, had cauſe to ſear that, this Information being delivered into that Parliament, they ſhould be treated as Criminals, were oblig'd to make Application to your Majeſty, who having taken Notice that this Proceeding was a Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and that the Parliament of Dijon was not competent to take Cognizance of this Affair, wherein the Religion was ſo much concern'd, remitted it to the ſaid Lord Bouchu, thereof, after Information taken to Judge with Sovereign Authority, and joyning to them in Commiſſion ſeven Graduats.</p>
            <p>This Power which made the ſaid Lord Bouchu ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Maſter of the Affair, wrought a notable change in the manner of his Proceedings, for whereas before he had treated them well, and teſtified to them, That he had all manner of Inclination to do them Juſtice for the Abuſes and Indignities they had ſuffered: They were ſurprized to find that in ſtead thereof, he had ſent to ſeek for the Information taken by the Lord Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melis, and having compared it with that of the Lord de Guijon, he had put one part of your Petitioners under an Arreſt, and obliged others of them, and ſome Catholiques alſo to a perſonal Appearance, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a new Commiſſion to the ſaid Lord Guijon, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108872:4"/> Criminal of Avalon, with an Aſſiſtant of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Proteſtant Religion to continue the Inquiſition, and to perfect the Proceſs unto Judgment excluſively, and, which was more ſtrange, he permitted his ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate to take Information more at large of all the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Inſtructions of your Majeſties Attorny, and of the ſaid Gray-Fryer du Han, that the Witneſſes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſaid Attorny might be examined upon the Contents of the ſaid Articles: which was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, for that the ſaid Gray-Fryer is dead to the World, and therefore uncapable to act and plead in Law: and beſides accuſed and convicted to have been the Boutefew or Incendiary of this popular Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and therefore could not be Plantiff, nor ought thoſe his Articles of Charge to be received, which were contrived for his own Diſcharge. This Partiality made way for another, which was that this Gray-Fryer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus authorized to give-in Articles, went on ſo far as to frame and obtain an injurious and ſcandalous Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt your Petitioners, whom he accuſed to have attempted to begin a Civil WAR in France by this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, of which, he ſuggeſted, they were the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: Which obliged them, when the firſt Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof was made, to interpoſe an Appeal, as againſt an Abuſe, which being ſignified to your Majeſties ſaid Attorney of the ſaid place of Avalon, he made a Return on the foot of the Writ, on the 5 of September, that he had done nothing therein nor known nothing thereof: and yet nevertheleſs when they would have ſtopt them from proceeding in the ſaid Publications, which tended towards new Seditions, the aforeſaid Delegate, of his own private Authority, ordained, That it ſhould go on: In purſuance whereof the ſaid Publications being made, there were at leaſt a Thouſand Witneſſes offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be examined, out of which the ſaid Gray-Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108872:5"/> choſe 206, who were the very ſame that followed his Orders in this Inſurrection, and cauſed them to be heard by the ſaid Lord Guijon the Delegate.</p>
            <p>But this Information, which was not finiſhed till the Month of November, was never yet concluded on, nor any Decretal Judgment made upon the Charges contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein, the ſaid Delegate contenting himſelf with the Judicial Decrees of Arreſt and perſonal Appearance, which the ſaid Lord Bouchu had made upon the firſt Informations, by his Ordinance of the 19th of Auguſt: which obliged your Petitioners, cited by thoſe Decrees, to apply themſelves again to your Majeſty, to whom it being repreſented, that by your firſt Order of the 6 of July, you had judged the Parliament of Dijon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent of that Affair, and conſequently the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation alſo that was taked by the Lord Chaumelis, an Aſſiſtant or Commiſſioner of the ſaid Parliament, (who had not called to him any Aſſiſtant of the pretended Proteſtant Religion) was alſo null, and ought not to have been regarded: Your Majeſty gave out another Order of the 24 of October, by which it was ordained, That in the Proſecution and Judgment of the ſaid Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, the ſaid Lord Bouchu ſhould have no regard to the Information of the Lord of Chaumelis, but only to thoſe taken by the ſaid Lord Guijon, and Rey de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, his Aſſiſtant; and what the ſaid Lord Bouchu would, ſhould cauſe to be made anew, and in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid form, on which he ſhould further execute the ſaid Order of the 6 of July, according to its Form and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure. In purſuance of which laſt Order, it is certain, That not only the ſaid Information of the ſaid Lord of Chaumelis, but the Decrees of perſonal Appearance and Arreſt of the ſaid Lord Bouchu, judged by his Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereon againſt your Petitioners, were vacated, and conſequently that the proceſs againſt them ought
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108872:5"/> to be made upon new Charges and new Decrees; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs upon them it is that the greater part of your Petitioners are Condemned as contumacious, and the Lord Bouchu hath given Judgment againſt them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other Information, and againſt all form of Law on the 30 of July laſt, having firſt declared by certain par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Catholicks, whom he cauſed preſently to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in perſon, and that the ſaid Charges and Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were ſufficient to ground the Proceſs.</p>
            <p>By this Judgment, (which without doubt will ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize your Majeſty) he hath declared the Defaults of ſix of your Petitioners, and four others to be legally taken and obtained, and to be effectual, giving Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them, and ſix others who appeared and put in their Defence; and for reparation of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ariſing from the Proceſs, he hath condemned your ſaid Orators alone in 6000 livers ſolid fine; whereof the ſaid Lords of Ollon, Barveil and Pougues were each to pay 1000 livers, and the Lords of Seurre, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, Henry and Iſaac de Bloſſet, each of them 750 li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers applicable to the following uſes; to wit, 1000 li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to your Majeſties benefit, 2000 to the Hoſpital of St. Reine, 1000 to that of Avalon, 600 to the Repairs of the Seſſions Houſe of the Bayliwick of Dijon, 300 li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to the Cloiſter of the Gray-Fryers of Vezelay, the like ſum of 300 livers to the Cloiſter of the Minnu Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Avalon, and another 300 livers to the Capou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins of the ſaid Avalon, and 150 livers to the Church of Vaujau-court, 200 livers to Zachary Courcelles for his Concerns, 150 to three other private perſons for their Concerns, and Joſhua Prevoſt and James Mugnier were condemned, and namely, the firſt in 20 livers fine, and 60 livers damage to Lazarus Perin, and the other in ten livers fine, and all theſe aforeſaid condemned to the whole Coſt and Charges of the ſute, and as for the ſaid
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108872:6"/> private Catholicks, they were diſcharged from attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Court, and quit of the Proceſs; and it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that John Gravier, Miniſter of Chaſtillon, ſhould be taken, arreſted and carried to the Royal Priſon of Dijon, to have his proceſs made and perfected, and to compleat this work, there is added that your Majeſty ſhould be very humbly petitioned to forbid the publick Exerciſe of the Proteſtant Religion through the whole extent of the ſaid Bayliwich of Avalon; and that to that intent the Churches wherein they keep that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſhould be ſpeedily pulled down and demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>This Judgment hath ſupprized and ſcandalized all the Country, even all the Catholicks that have any lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Juſtice in them, ſeeing that inſtead of puniſhing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily this popular Fury, which was terrible to all people; the aſſaulted, and rather they who were Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred paid the Fine; the damage and charges are given to the Murderers; and beyond all this; both they and all the Inhabitants of the Bayliwick of Avalon were menaced to be deprived of the Exerciſe of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that very Churches which eſcaped in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and had undergone the examination made of its Titles by the ſaid Lord Bouchu beaten down and demoliſhed; the Hoſpital and Cloyſters of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try round enriched with their Spoils, and that in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular whereof the ſaid Du Hau was Warden, who was the Author and Promoter of the Furyes and Plunders exerciſed on the Petitioners, their Houſes and Goods, and which is very extraordinary; That this Gray-Fryer, who pretends, and is, according to the Laws of France, the Statutes and Vows of his Order, civilly Dead; hath no right to bring any Sute or Action, and was both accuſed and convicted Legally and Juſtly, and could be at, nor have no Charges, it being one of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108872:6"/> the Vows of his Order; that he touch no money at all; hath notwithſtanding obtained a Decree for his Expenſes, which he hath ſince cauſed to be rated at Three Thouſand Three Hundred and Forty two livers, one penny half penny, by an Execution, where he hath ſerved the Petitioners, with a Proteſtation upon their Refuſal, to cauſe their Goods to be ſeized and ſold: all which tends to the giving Licentious Indulgence to ſuch people as are Seditiouſly enclined againſt them of the Proteſtant Religion; but alſo to ſuch Preachers who are but too much enclined to inſtigate them againſt ſuch who will give ear to them. Whereupon neither your Petitioners, nor any other of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, can be in any ſecurity, whereby your Majeſty may perceive of what Importance it is, and how neceſſary that ſome ſingle Sovereign Judge be conſtituted, and liberty given him to chooſe his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants; and particularly a ſupreme Intendant, who may make choiſe of ſuch Aſſiſtants to him, as are not too much obliged to complyance and ſubmiſſion; of which the Lord Bouchu without doubt, if any is to be ſuſpected, who having been forced by evident proofs of the exerciſe of the Proteſtant Religion in the Vaujau-court to confirm it, was not diſpleaſed to have this occaſion given him, to declare your Petitioners crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in this popular Sedition, that he might thence take an occaſion to put to the end of his Judgment this Petition to your Majeſty, to deprive all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſaid Baylliwick, the liberty of ſerving God, and to ordain the demolition of all their Churches. But this Soverainty which was given him did not extend to diſpenſe with him from obſerving all forms common and neceſſary for the Conviction of the Guilty.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:108872:7"/>
            <p>Now that your Majeſty may know he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and violated the moſt eſſential Procedures, you are beſought to conſider, That there have been three Bills of Complaint. The firſt taken by the Lord Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Lieutenant, Criminal of Avalon, and upon this there can be no pretence, to ſay; That your Petitioners could be condemned, for that it was taken upon their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, the Contents whereof was very well proved by 60 Witneſſes, which they produced and cauſed to be examined, who named and convicted the Authors and Actors of that Conſpiracy. The ſecond, which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the inſtigation of the ſaid Gray Fryer du Hau, at the inſtance of the Attorny General for the Parliament of Dyon, by the Lord Caumelis was declared Null, by your Majeſties Order, granted the 14. of October, which without doubt did extend to nullify alſo the Decrees judged by the ſaid Lord Bouchu, upon the Complaints contained therein: There remains only then the third Indictment, by 206 Witneſſes, put-in in September, and finiſhed in November, upon which the Lord Bouchu could find any complaint or charge to found his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but firſt of all that is Null, being made to the prejudice of an Appeal of Abuſe, in the grant of that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, which Abuſe conſiſted in this: That the grant of that Indictment could not legally be obtained, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the permiſſion of a royal Judge, which ought always to go before the Cognizance of the Cauſe, it being not in the power of parties to publiſh Indictments and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, according to their own fancies, nor to have them granted and publiſhed, for otherwiſe many dangerous Informations, and ſuch as might have very bad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, might be made publick, and ſuch indeed in the preſent caſe they were in which the Gray-Fryer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigated by labouring for his own Diſcharge, had and made uſe of that in his Information, whereof he was the ſole Author; as namely, That your Petitioners and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108872:7"/> others who were Aſſembled at Vaujaucourt, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to make an Inſurrection, to begin a Civil War in France; a ridiculous Calumny amongſt reaſonable perſons, which nevertheleſs was very apt to put Stones and other Weapons into the hands of the Rabble, very credulous and eaſily moved to Inſurrections, Slaughter and Plunder, whence it appears that ſuch a permiſſion was neceſſary in this caſe, according to the conſtant uſe of all the Juriſdictions of the Kingdom, but that it ought alſo to have been agreed and limitted by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the ſaid Judge, and not left to the diſcretion of a paſſionate Monk; and it is certain that the Lord Bouchu himſelf, ought to have reduced it by his diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſupportable terms, becauſe this is a point of higheſt conſequence in the judgement of a Sute, and and not to have left it to a Sub-delegate, to whom he could have only committed the ſimple proſecution and information, and not that which might give the deciſive blow to the chief concern, or iſſue of the cauſe. There was alſo an Abuſe or Error in regard of the perſon who obtained this S n ence, which was the Gray Fryer alone, notwithſtanding he neither was nor could be a party to the Sute, but your Majeſties Attorney, only who decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red when the ſaid Appeal upon abuſe was ſignified to him, that he had no notice of the Sentence, nor of the publication made thereof: Add hereto, that by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the ſaid Lord Bouchu, of the 19. of Auguſt no Witneſſes ought to have been examined, but ſuch as ſhould have been appointed by your Majeſties Attorney; whence it follows, that the 20 Witneſſes who were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined to the ſaid laſt Sentence, being pick't by the ſaid Gray Fryer du Han, out of more then 1200, which were propounded to be examined. This Indictment or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was alſo Null, being it muſt needs be preſumed, That this Monk would chuſe none but his Accomplices
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108872:8"/> in his Fury, who, for their own and his diſcharge, would be careful not to fail in accuſing your Petitioners: and this is very conſiderable, becauſe of another Nullity ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the proceedings of the Lord Bouchu, which is omitting the Re-examination of the Witneſſes, and confronting them with the Defendents, which formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are for certain abſolutely neceſſary to perfect and put the laſt hand to criminal Proceſſes, that are of any conſequence. The Re-examination conſiſts in this, that the witneſſes who proves any charge being ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a ſecond time for this purpoſe, and appearing before the Judge, his Depoſition be read unto him, to know whether he perſiſt therein, and whether he have any thing to add to it, or take from it: and Confronting is the preſenting the Witneſſes and the Defendant face to face, that on the one hand the Witneſs may declare whether he know the Defendant, and whether he be the perſon againſt whom he depoſes; and on the other ſide, the Defendant may ſay, whether he know the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and whether he may be creditable or he have ſome exception againſt him, which he is obliged to make pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, otherwiſe he will not be allowed; ſee here what is obſervable on the behalf of the Defendant, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to make any Defence by way of croſs Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories put into the Judge, and preſents himſelf to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted by the Witneſſes, and for them who make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault by not appearing, and contumacy, there is a re-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the witneſſes only had, that ſerves inſtead of a confrontation, which in this caſe is termed imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. Now, as for the private Catholicks, who were of the number of the Seditions, there was no need of confrontation nor re-examination for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned them, for there being nothing from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Decreed againſt them, but that they ſhould appear perſonally, they preſented themſelves, and having made
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108872:8"/> their Defence, and finding the Lord Bouchu diſpoſed to treat them favourably, they declared that they would be judged of that which was charged againſt them, but as to your Petitioners, who of Plaintiffs were made Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and of Accuſers accuſed, and perceived very well by the firſt Decrees that the Lord Bouchu made againſt them, as ſoon as he was declared their Soveraign Judge, that he had a deſign to treat them as Criminals, they were very far from declaring that they would take judgement on the charges depoſed againſt them, by ſuch Witneſſes as were themſeves guilty of the Violences and Robberies committed againſt them; ſo that the Lord Bouchu ought, if he would condemn them, to have obſerved againſt them all the ordinary formaliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: In doing which, he ought firſt to have paſt Sentence on your Petitioners Appeal of Abuſe, againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment granted againſt them, the ſcandalous Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, had produced that cloud of 1000 Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: after that if he could have convinced the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and had judged the Indictment valid, whereof the Witneſſes had been prict, not by the Attorney Royal, but by the Gray Fryer, then he ſhould have conſulted with his Aſſiſtant, and made the new decretal Orders againſt the Petitioners, and have cauſed them to be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified unto them, to obliged them to appear, put in their defence, and abide the confrontation of the Witneſſes againſt them, and thereupon to re-examine the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and confront them effectually againſt them that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and by ſuppoſition againſt thoſe who made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault: but, for certain, there was nothing done of all this, but he ſtuck to his firſt Decrees, though they were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled by your Majeſties Order of the 24. of October, as well as the Information taken by the Lord Chammelis, upon which his Judgement was made; and this is the ſorry foundation on which he hath built and taken ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108872:9"/> of your Petitioners as contumacious, becauſe they would not appear upon his firſt Decrees, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out citing them by Writ according to uſe, and without re-examination of Witneſſes, he condemned them by his Judgment.</p>
            <p>As for what concerns the Lord D'Ollon he appeared before him, made his Defence as he was required, which was alſo taken only two days before the ſaid Judgment, he ſtill declaring that he was ready to abide the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frontation of the Witneſſes, if any of them could give in any charge againſt him.</p>
            <p>It cannot be pretended that he was wanting in any thing, but on the contrary he would have been well pleaſed that the ſaid Witneſſes had been preſented to him, becauſe he could eaſily have excepted againſt them, and have convinced them to have been them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of all the Diſorder; neither would any other proof have been needed againſt them than the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment brought againſt them at the beginning, at the requeſt of the Petitioner; wherein it was by 60 unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable Witneſſes, That thoſe who were laſt examined, who inſiſted on any charge, were they who executed the Conſpiracy againſt the Aſſembly of the Synod, where your Petitioners were Aſſaulted, Wounded, Murdered, Maſſacred, dragg'd by the hair, left for dead, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney they had about them rob'd from them, and their Hats, Swords, Belts and Coats, and the reſt of their Cloaths torn in pieces, and many of their Houſes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up and plundered, and all this at the ſound of the Alarm Bell, and with a continual cry of Harlau, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lau againſt the Hugonets, which is the word to raiſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Nor can any Compariſon be made betwixt theſe two Informations, becauſe the former was made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all the forms of Law, and was confirmed and authorized by your Majeſties Order, of the 24 of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108872:9"/> whereas this latter is a pure recrimination, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely null, in that it was made contrary to all Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Order: and it is to be conſidered that the Catholicks who were ſummoned at firſt upon the former Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and did perſonally appear, knowing that they were convicted of Violence and Robbery, did acknowledge one part of their Charge, That they had entred into the Houſes of the Proteſtants, and taken ſome of their Goods, believing that it was allowed them, and that the Plunder had been given the Catholicks; and this notwithſtanding, by the Judgment of the Lord Bouchu, they were purely and ſimply diſmiſſed and diſcharged from the Court and Sute, without condemning them to the Reſtitution of what they had Robbed.</p>
            <p>This Judgment wherein he took to him no Aſſiſtant of the Proteſtant Religion, can therefore neither ſubſiſt in form and matter, being it is againſt all Rules of Legal Proceedings, and againſt Juſtice, which cannot allow that the Guilty, convicted both by their own confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and good proofs, whereunto they have nothing to object, whereon they have joyned Iſſue, ſhould be ſent away abſolved, and the Gentlemen who had always li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Peace, and with all Sweetneſs and Moderation in the Country, without being ever accuſed of the leaſt Violence, and who, on all occaſions when they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to your Majeſties Service, have behaved themſelves according to their Duty; and finally, who have by the ſame Information proved by 60 unreprovable Witneſſes, that they have no hand, nor were any partakers of the Sedition in Queſtion, but only as they were the ſad and unhappy objects thereof, who ſuffered therein all imaginable Outrages and Indignities, and yet are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in great penalties, as ſome great and criminal Offenders, and threatned to be deprived as ſeditious perſons, of that which is more dear unto them than
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108872:10"/> their Lives, to wit, the Liberty of their Conſcience, and Exerciſe of their Religion in their Churches.</p>
            <p>This Judgement is not at all difinitive, for if it had been given in Parliament, or in ſome Soveraign Court, the Petitioners, who are condemned as contumatious, would always, or for five years at leaſt, have liberty to appear, make their defence, and ſubmit to Confrontati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and it is certain, That their appearance only would annul the Sentence of their Condemnation, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults and contumacy. But they moſt humbly pray your Majeſty, that they may not be conſtrained to appear before the Lord Bouchu, and to acknowledge him for their Soveraign Judge, after ſo irregular and unjuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, as he hath uſed in the ſaid Indictment and Judgement upon the whole Sute: They require not to be diſmiſſed and abſolved, upon what they report of their Innocency, nor that they ſhould be condemned upon their ſimple Affirmation whom they accuſe, to have conſpired to Maſſacre them, and to have exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them the cruelties and robberies, which have been above declared, all this appears in the conſideration of the Cauſe: There are two Informations, The one taken upon your Petitioners complaint and requeſt, in which there is no defect, and your Majeſty hath judged it good and valid, by your Sentence of the four and twentieth of October, and, as for the other it is Null by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons related above, which are of much greater force than thoſe whereby your Majeſty was induced to vacate and reject, by the firm Sentence which the Lord Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melis had made, in that beſides the recrimination which is common to both the Indictment in hand, had for its foundation an abuſive monitory citation, obtained by a Criminal Monk, and without making your Majeſties Attorney party thereunto, who alone had power to proſecute the Information upon the Proceſs and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108872:10"/> the Witneſſes, and who would not have taken the way of a monitory citation, in a matter wherein it can never be allowed, in regard it is not poſſible to have juſtice againſt a Sedition, if means be given to the Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to prevent themſelves, and to be Witneſses in their own Cauſe, and for their own juſtification; and for the Lord Bouchu without doubt cannot be diſpoſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and reject that which he hath already approved, and other Judges will make great difficulty to do it, your Majeſty is moſt humbly beſought, to paſs Sentence, as you have already done of the nullity of the Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord Chaumelis, and to give them other Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ſuch as are not ſuſpected of partiality againſt your Petitioners, both to determine on the firſt Information, and to take others if they judge it needful, and to make an end of ſitting this Proceſs, for Re-hearing.</p>
            <p>This conſidered, Great Sir, and the Importance of the affair, whereon there is queſtion of doing Juſtice, on a Sedition of this nature and quality, for ſecuring the repoſe and tranquility of the Country: May it pleaſe your Majeſty, without inſiſting on the Ordinance of the Lord Bo chu, of the nineteenth of Auguſt 1667. and all that which is don and enſued thereupon, to ſend back unto ſome Royal Court of the Province of Burgundy, other than that of Avalon, the Inſtruction, Iſsue and Judgement of this Sute; and to Ordain, That to this end the firſt information taken by the Lord Guijon and Rey de morande his Aſſiſtant, be brought thither viewed, and determined, and a new one taken thereon, if it be neceſsary, by good Witneſſes to be produced, by your Majeſties Attorny of the ſaid Court, on whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and inſtance, and not of any other, the ſaid Judgement may be wholy made, an Aſſiſtant of the Reformed Religion, being Aſſumed to him therein, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Edict at Nants, and the ſaid Order of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108872:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the 24 of October, all without prejudice to an Appeal to one of the Chambers of the Edict, unleſs your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will rather be pleaſed to aſſume the cauſe, and give Judgment therein you ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>And your Petitioners ſhall continue their Prayers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for your Majeſties Health and Proſperity.</salute>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>But this Petition avail'd nothing for redreſs of theſe Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces complained of by the Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THis Tranſlation and ſeveral other Pieces were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Preſs ſome time before this Plot broke out, and attended till Now, a convenient ſeaſon for their Publication.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ez. Tonge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is lately Publiſhed The Univerſal Diſpenſatory, Contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as the Preface to it ſhews you) the Choiſeſt things in the <hi>Auguſtan Dispenſatory,</hi> in <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> in <hi>Horſtius,</hi> in <hi>Faber, Sala, Quercetan, Hartman, Schroder, Mynſicht,</hi> &amp;c. in ſhort, 'tis the Sum of all the moſt excellent Deſignations from the greateſt Scholars, the profoundeſt Wits, the moſt wiſe, induſtrious and experienced Phyſicians, through all Ages to this day, whether Greek, Latin or Engliſh; thereby rendring this Work the moſt compleat of any thing that is or can be in that kind: Its Title Page is <hi>Pharmacopoeia Londinenſis Reformata. Or, the</hi> New London Diſpenſatory. <hi>In ſix Books. Tranſlated into Engliſh for the publick Good, and fitted to the whole Art of Healing. Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Preparations, Virtues and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of all Simple Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments; Vegitable, Animal and Mineral: Of all Compounds, both Internal and External: And of all the Chymical Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions now in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe. Together with ſeveral choiſe Medicines added by the Author. As alſo the</hi> Praxis <hi>of</hi> Chymiſtry, <hi>as it's now Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, fitted to the meaneſt Capacity. By</hi> William Salmon <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Phyſick. To which is added a Table, ſhewing the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the Text and Comment, neceſſary to be known by every Student. Printed for</hi> Th. Dawks, Th. Baſſet, J. Wright <hi>and</hi> R. Chiſwel. 1679. Price Bound 7 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
